<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the Hague, at the funeral of the late Prince of Orange (father to his present Majesty King William III.) who died in the year 1650. wherein the life and actions of his present Majesty are prophetically foretold. By the learned Mr. Morus. Translated out of French by Daniel la Fite, M.A. rector of Woolavington in Sussex.</title>
            <author>More, Alexander, 1616-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216378</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828109</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828109</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32536</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51278)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32536)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1855:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the Hague, at the funeral of the late Prince of Orange (father to his present Majesty King William III.) who died in the year 1650. wherein the life and actions of his present Majesty are prophetically foretold. By the learned Mr. Morus. Translated out of French by Daniel la Fite, M.A. rector of Woolavington in Sussex.</title>
                  <author>More, Alexander, 1616-1670.</author>
                  <author>Lafite, Daniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.D. for Roger Clavel, at the Peacock in Fleetstreet.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCIV. [1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an initial imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  II, --  Prince of Orange, 1626-1650 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32536:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at the <hi>HAG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E,</hi> At the FUNERAL of the Late <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> (Father to his preſent MAJESTY King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> III.) Who died in the Year 1650. Wherein the Life and Actions of his preſent Majeſty are Prophetically foretold.</p>
            <p>By the Learned Mr. <hi>MORUS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French by <hi>Daniel la Fite,</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Woolavington</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Roger Clavel,</hi> at the Peacock in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCXCIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:32536:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <p>Junii 28. 1694.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>RA. BARKER.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32536:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:32536:3"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32536:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH XL. 6, 7, 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>The Voice ſaid, Cry. And he ſaid, What ſhall I cry? All Fleſh is Graſs, and all the Glory thereof is as the Flower of the Field. The Graſs withereth, the Flower fadeth; becauſe the Spirit of the Lord bloweth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: Surely the People is Graſs. The Graſs withereth, the Flower fadeth; but the Word of our God ſhall ſtand for ever.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Heavens declare the Glory of God, ſaith the Prophet; and though they have neither Speech nor Language, yet for all that is their Voice heard: They ſpeak not to him that liſtens, but to him that views them, and entertain him much to this purpoſe; Conſider well our Beauty and Luſtre, the Vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Bodies, the unerring Stedfaſtneſs of our Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Univerſality of our Influences: We have not fram'd our ſelves, we are the Effects of the Firſt Cauſe, the Productions of a Wiſe and Omnipotent God. What the Prophet aſſerts of the Heavens, the ſame we may ſay of the Dead, and that in a more emphatical and ſignificant manner; They declare the Glory of God, and the Empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Vanity of Man; there is no Speech nor Language with them, no nor Motion neither, as there is in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bodies, yet is their Speech heard; and if we hear
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32536:4"/>them not, 'tis not becauſe they don't ſpeak, but becauſe we do not hearken: They ſpeak, they preach, they cry with a Voice intelligible enough, (even with the dumb Language of their loud and inſtructive Silence) Behold and ſee to what we are come, and whither you are going; God, who by his Almighty Word ſpoke us out of the Duſt by withdrawing his Breath, hath return'd us thither again. But above all the Great Dead ſpeak loudeſt, and with a moſt diſtinguiſhing Tone, with a Voice like to that of many Waters, with a Voice that breaks the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> in his Life-time, was both a King and a Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; he made a Pulpit of his Throne, and gave himſelf the Name of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> that is to ſay, a Preacher. But if <hi>Solomon</hi> was a Preacher when alive, all Kings and Princes become ſuch when they die: they preach to all the World, and the very ſame thing that he, the wiſeſt of Men, and happieſt of Kings, had preached before them; <hi>Vanity of Vanities, all is Vanity!</hi> which is no other than what is here proclaimed by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> I might as well have ſaid Prince <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> for he was indeed a Prince of the Blood Royal, and yet died as well as the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> who, as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> obſerves, was a Cow-herd; ſo that dying as well as living he cried, <hi>All Fleſh is Graſs, and all the Glory thereof is as the Flower of the Field.</hi> But alas! why is this Text ſo plain? why ſo convincingly evident? and ſo eaſy to be underſtood? O that it were a Riddle yet, and hard to be apprehended: but we have all of us too ſenſible a Demonſtration of this Truth, and we can ſay nothing for the clearing of it, which is not much inferiour to the Evidence which our common Diſaſter gives us thereof. Had I a golden Tongue, as that famous Biſhop of old, or were I inſpired with the Eloquence of Angels, yet ſhould not I be able to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32536:4"/>ſay any thing that would come near to the Clearneſs and Force of the ſad Commentary which <hi>the Breath of our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, He of whom we ſaid, Many Nations ſhall reſt under his Shadow,</hi> hath given us upon it. I ſhall not need therefore to take ſo much care to explain the Words, as otherwiſe I ſhould be obliged to do. The thing it ſelf ſpeaks; his Highneſs, though dead, ſpeaks; yea cries, <hi>All Fleſh is Graſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Fleſh,</hi> that is, without any Exception. Men have many Advantages, and more eſpecially theſe two, <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Speech,</hi> which diſtinguiſh them from all other living Creatures; but as for the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> there is nothing very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary in it: one of the moſt obſcene and impure Beaſts, the Swine, is very like Man, as to his inward Parts; and as to the outward, the moſt ill-favour'd and ridiculous of all Creatures expreſſeth him beſt. Our Fleſh is of the ſame Subſtance and Form with the Creatures we feed upon. Wherefore, what is Man? but as an ancient Philiſopher ſaid, a little <hi>Flegm</hi> and <hi>Gall</hi> put together, that is to ſay, a Mixture of Water and Fire; or, if you will, of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> Indeed Man, as to his Body, is nothing elſe but mere Fleſh and Blood, altogether inclin'd to Corruption, and nothing but Frailty, according to the Hebrew Phraſe; for when the Jews would ſpeak with Contempt of a thing, that is of no Conſtancy or Solidity, they call it <hi>Baſharve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> Fleſh and Blood.</p>
            <p>You muſt not imagine that our Prophet ſpeaking here of <hi>Fleſh,</hi> intends thereby <hi>Sin only,</hi> or the corrupt Nature of Man, as our Saviour does when he ſaith, <hi>That which is born of the Fleſh is Fleſh;</hi> for had this been his meaning, he would not have ſaid, <hi>All Fleſh,</hi> but reſtrained his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to the Fleſh of Sinners. Therefore when he ſays, <hi>All Fleſh,</hi> his meaning is, that all Men, the moſt godly and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32536:5"/>righteous not excepted, are ſubject to Death: All the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Adam,</hi> inaſmuch as they are made up of Fleſh and Blood, muſt return to their Original Duſt as well as he.</p>
            <p>But perhaps you will ſay, Of what avail is it then to us, that we are the Children of God, if we muſt inevitably ſubmit to Death as well as other Men? I anſwer; the New Birth was not deſign'd to preſerve us in the State wherein <hi>Adam</hi> was created, nor to reſtore us to it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that was but a carnal and periſhable Eſtate, but to exalt us to the glorious Condition of <hi>the Second Adam,</hi> who is <hi>the Man from Heaven,</hi> altogether ſpiritual and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal. Indeed <hi>Adam</hi> in his State of Innocence was but Fleſh and Blood; for though he knew no Sin, yet was he liable to Sin, and conſequently to Death, which is the Wages of it. <hi>Fleſh and Blood,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul, cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom of God.</hi> What think you doth the Apoſtle mean here by <hi>Fleſh and Blood?</hi> He doth not mean Sin, though what he ſaith be true of Sin too; but in this place, as appears from the Context, is underſtood Humane Nature, conſider'd in its Infirmities, though otherwiſe innocent and juſt, as ſubject to a continual Changeableneſs, to a troubleſome Viciſſitude of Eating and Drinking, of Labour and Reſt, and to many other Drudgeries and Neceſſities of Life, becauſe in this State it cannot ſubſiſt before God, no more than Wax before the burning Sun.</p>
            <p>Furthermore; if you ask me, Why it is that all <hi>Fleſh is Graſs,</hi> ſubject to Fading and Death? I anſwer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without Death we cannot inherit the Kingdom of Heaven. It was impoſſible even for <hi>Adam,</hi> all innocent and all juſt as he was, to be tranſported to Heaven with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leaving his Fleſh behind him, or without undergoing ſome Change, which might deveſt him of his natural
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32536:5"/>Infirmities, and endow him with Divine and Spiritual Qualities. And would you aſpire to the Glory of this Kingdom, without putting off the old Rags of your cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Nature? Nothing that is defiled or impure ſhall ever enter into it; nor any thing that is of an earthy and corruptible Nature. Don't therefore ask me any more, why the Fleſh, even of the Children of God, is as Graſs, or why they muſt unavoidably die. There are two obvious Reaſons for it, and ſuch as you cannot be ignorant of: The firſt is, becauſe of their Sin; the ſecond, becauſe of their Infirmity and Corruptibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>The Angels were Sinners, but had no Fleſh, and conſequently were not ſubject to Mortality; <hi>Adam</hi> was mortal, as being made up of Fleſh and Blood, but was no Sinner: nevertheleſs, neither the Angels, after they had ſinn'd, nor <hi>Adam</hi> who had never ſinn'd, could ever bear the Preſence of God. The Sinfulneſs of the Fallen Angels could not bear his Juſtice; and the infirm and corruptible Nature of Man could not bear the Glory of his Divine Majeſty: and we who are both infirm Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals and Sinners, how could we appear before his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Juſtice, or endure his tranſcendent Glory, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being ſtruck down to the Ground, without being overſet and ſwallowed up by them? Our Bodies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt by Death be caſt into the Grave, as into a Melting-pot, to be melted down, and to be caſt a-new. Death is the true Purgatory; here the Saints are refined, here they put off all the Remains of Corruption, by quitting the caſt Skin of the Old Man, and all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of their Fleſh. But the Prophet here cries out, <hi>All Fleſh,</hi> without confining himſelf either to the Fleſh of Sin, or to the Fleſh of Weakneſs and Corruptibility:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32536:6"/>
               <hi>All Fleſh,</hi> all that we ſee, all that charms and flatters our Senſes, all thoſe painted Deluſions, all thoſe gay Colours and pleaſant Pictures; yea, the whole World, with all that is in it, is all but Fleſh, and all <hi>Fleſh is as Graſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men being ſenſible that their Fleſh muſt return to the Earth, whence it was taken, endeavour at leaſt to preſerve the Memory of it by dead but durable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations, ſuch as Pictures, Statues, Triumphal Arches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But there is no Matter, no Induſtry that is of Proof againſt the devouring Teeth of Time, the ſecret Force of that powerful Corroſive waſtes by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and defaces, ſooner or later, Coloſſus's, Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mides and Mauſoleums: Marble and Braſs indeed laſt longer than our Bodies, yet in proceſs of Time they crumble away, and thereby demonſtrate they were but Fleſh and Corruption, Duſt and Aſhes. All the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Objects you gaze and dote upon, with ſo much Wonder and Love, are but Apples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> fair and tempting to the Eye, but worm-eaten and rotten with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. The Colour that ſhines outwardly is gay and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing; but all this Paint covers nothing but Duſt and Aſhes, and ſtill at the bottom all is but Graſs, which is green and flouriſhing for a while, but ſoon after turns to Hay, dry'd, faded and dead, without any Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, Strength or Virtue. <hi>O Earth, Earth, Earth, hear the World of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 22.29.</note> cries the Prophet <hi>Jeremy:</hi> In which Exclamation he intends Man, who is thrice Earth, becauſe he was made of Earth, becauſe he feeds on Earth, and becauſe having lingred and crept for a time upon it, at laſt returns into the Belly of the Earth, our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Mother.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:32536:6"/>
            <p>The Condition of Man is much the ſame with thoſe Plants ſhall I call them, or living Creatures, call'd <hi>Plantanimals,</hi> which being faſtned by the Belly to the Earth, brouze and eat up all the Graſs they find with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their reach, and then die for lack of Nouriſhment. But it may be ſome will ſay, that this may paſs for Truth, in reference to the common ſort of People, and the Scum of Men; but that the Heroes, the Monarchs, the Conquerors of Nations, the Thunder-bolts of War, have ſomething that raiſes them above thoſe vulgar and creeping Souls. Our Prophet, in ſome reſpect, ſeems to agree to this, for he puts ſome Difference between a poor and a rich Man, between a Subject and a Prince: But alas! what Difference is it? Why, ſuch as there is between green Graſs and a fine Flower, which by its lively and luſtrous Colour, ſhines like a Star in a Medow; for ſo the ancient Poets, by a witty Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor, called Flowers, the Stars of the Earth. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties of Men are not without their Stars; but theſe Stars fall and become extinguiſh'd: nor without their Lillies and Roſes, but theſe Roſes have their Prickles, and theſe Lillies are as ſhort-liv'd as they are ſweet and pleaſant. The Lillies of the Field outvie <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his Glory; but for all this are ſtill but poor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Flowers, more gay and beautiful indeed, but not leſs periſhing than others. The tall Cedar, as well as the Hyſop that grows on the Wall, the Flowers as well as the Graſs of the Field, all fade, and all periſh. And this is the Reaſon why our Prophet, after that he had ſaid, <hi>All Fleſh is Graſs,</hi> adds, <hi>And all the Glory thereof is as the Flower of the Field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He underſtands, by the <hi>Glory thereof,</hi> its Luſtre and Beauty, its Grace and Splendor, its Strength and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32536:7"/>its Gayety and Pomp, whatſoever in it is moſt ſweet, pleaſing and raviſhing: In a word, all that daz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Pomp and Show, which the Prince of Darkneſs diſplay'd before the Eyes of the Prince of Life; all the Kingdoms of the Earth, with all their Glory.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Glory,</hi> according to the Stile of the Jews, comprehends the three capital good things wherein Men generally place their Bliſs and Happineſs, to wit, <hi>Profit, Honour</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure;</hi> for theſe are the three De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons that poſſeſs all Men: <hi>Covetouſneſs, Ambition</hi> and <hi>Voluptuouſneſs,</hi> divide all Mankind, and are the Trinity the World ſo much adores. The word <hi>Glory</hi> takes in all theſe three; it ſignifies <hi>Riches</hi> in that Expreſſion of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi>'s Children concerning <hi>Jacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 31.1.</note> 
               <hi>Of that which was our Fathers, hath he gotten all his Glory:</hi> It is taken for <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> as when St. <hi>Jude</hi> calls Princes and Magiſtrates <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Jude, <hi>v.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Glories,</hi> which we tranſlate <hi>Dignities:</hi> And for <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> where mention is made of <hi>the Glory of</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<hi>'s Court,</hi> that is, its Bravery, Pleaſures and Delights. Whence it is that we read in the New Teſtament of <hi>Riches of Glory,</hi> of a <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> and of <hi>a Joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable and full of Glory.</hi> And therefore this Word has been ſingled out to expreſs the full Enjoyment of all good things in the Life to come, becauſe there we ſhall have wherewith to give plenary Satisfaction to all our Wiſhes, <hi>Treaſures, Pleaſures</hi> and <hi>Honours,</hi> without Stint or Bound in their Nature, Meaſure or Durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>So that we are to underſtand by the <hi>Glory of the Fleſh,</hi> the condition of a Man who wants nothing, neither Riches, nor Pleaſures, nor Honours. Take, ſaith our Prophet, <hi>Fleſh</hi> in the fulleſt Enjoyment and Plenty of all things, in the moſt flouriſhing Gayety, Pomp, Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32536:7"/>and Luſtre, at the very top of Honour; yea, though upon a Throne, though abounding with immenſe Riches, though having his Enemies lying at his Feet, and being Maſter of the whole World; yet in the midſt of all theſe Joys, Elevations and Triumph, he will be liable to that damping Thought, But for all this thou art mortal, and all this muſt end in Death. All this Pomp and Triumph is but of one Day; 'tis but a Flower of the Field; and this Flower is an Herb, which though blown and flouriſhing, yet is ſtill but an Herb; and all the Glory and Goodlineſs thereof nothing but <hi>Fleſh</hi> well painted and trimly deck'd indeed; yet, for all that, at the bottom nothing but <hi>Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Flower is no leſs fading, periſhing, nor leſs ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be trod under foot, or to be ſcorch'd and wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Sun, than the Graſs is: As they grow in the ſame Field, they are liable to be cut down with the Edge of the ſame Sithe or Sickle. When the Harveſt is come, Death ſpares none, ſingles out none, but mows down all with his dreadful Sithe, Rich and Poor, Nobles and Commons, Bond and Free, Graſs and Flowers, without making any Diſtinction at all. <hi>But the Word of our God ſhall ſtand for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You expected probably that the Prophet would have oppoſed Fleſh to Spirit, and the Body to the Soul, and that he would have expreſs'd himſelf to this purpoſe; All Fleſh is as Graſs, but the Mind of Man is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Flame, and Celeſtial Light, which can never be extinguiſh'd, and his Soul is immortal. But no ſuch thing: there is nothing, ſaith he, but the Word of God that is Eternal; if the Soul of Man be not born again of the incorruptible Seed of this Word, don't flatter it with lying Titles, don't call it immortal after that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32536:8"/>the Judg of the World hath pronounc'd this unerring and irrevocable Sentence, <hi>The Soul that ſins, it ſhall die.</hi> This is the Stile of the Prophets, not of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: theſe indeed take great Pains to evince by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the Immortality of the Soul, but the former teach us that Souls die an Eternal Death, when the Word of the Lord is not found rooted and ingrafted in them. This is the only Principle of Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, without which the Soul's Immortality will only ſerve to plunge it into a Death; nay, into a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand cruel Deaths, and that eternally. The Immortality of the Soul conſiſts only in its Holineſs and Conformity to God.</p>
            <p>But conſider we further, the Oppoſition the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet makes here of the Word of God to all the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the World. This latter cannot, with all the Efforts of her Vanity, ſo much as make one Flower, nor the leaſt Spire of Graſs; whereas the Word of God hath made all things, and ſtill ſupports and upholds all it hath made, even the whole Univerſe. The Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the World ſheds and ſhews all its Luſtre, all its Force on the Surface of things: if you pry beyond that, the Inſide is nothing but Miſery, nothing but Frailty: The Word of God, on the contrary, carries its Treaſure in an Earthen Veſſel; outwardly to look upon it, nothing ſeems more weak, nothing more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible; 'tis a Voice crying in the Wilderneſs, 'tis a Man that ſpeaks, a poor Mortal; it ſeems but a beating of the Air, a Sound which the Wind carries away as faſt as it is uttered. And yet by this weak Inſtrument, by the Fooliſhneſs of Preaching, God brings forth his Wonders, gaining the Heart by the Ear, and convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to himſelf, and planting in it by his Spirit, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32536:8"/>ſacred Sprig of Eternal Life. <hi>The Words that I ſpeak, they are Spirit, they are Life. The Heavens and Earth ſhall paſs away, but my Word ſhall never paſs away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I, as briefly as I could, conſider'd my <hi>Text.</hi> I ſhall now, in the next place, apply it to the preſent occaſion. <hi>The Voice ſaith, Cry:</hi> but to whom ſhall I cry? To thee O Lord? but thou art offended: To the Angels and Saints? but they cannot hear me: To the Thrones of the Earth?<note n="*" place="margin">King <hi>Charles</hi> had been behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two Years before.</note> but they are caſt down: To our Prince? but he can no longer hear; and yet he ſpeaks: I will therefore repeat his Voice to thy People, and cry, <hi>All Fleſh is Graſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a Voice that cries, <hi>O my Son!</hi> another, <hi>O my Husband!</hi> and others, <hi>my Brother!</hi> and another would cry,<note n="†" place="margin">The Princeſs was then big with Child of this our King.</note> if he could, <hi>O my Father!</hi> So many other Voices cry, <hi>my Fortune</hi> and <hi>Well being:</hi> The whole Church hath mourned, and all <hi>Europe</hi> hath lamented. But all the Voices that compoſe the ſeveral Notes of this mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Harmony, do all accord and concenter in this Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, that <hi>all Fleſh is Graſs, and all the Glory thereof as the Flower of the Field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imagine his Highneſs, by a Miracle, ſtanding again upon his Feet in this Place, where he has ſo often ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and where he did ſo often diſplay the Beams of his Light, and of his Joy, and crying in this Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; who would not be moved at it, who would not be touch'd at the bottom of their Hearts? But there is no need of all this, when without ſtanding, without walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſtark dead, and without Motion, as he is, he ceaſeth not to cry out. Yea, his very being without Motion is that which ſpeaketh loudeſt to us, and proclaims, as by a Voice from Heaven, that the empty Scheme and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32536:9"/>Faſhion of this World paſſeth away, and we our ſelves together with it. The Throne leaves ſome, and others leave it; and as there is but one Kingdom that cannot be ſhaken in the Heavens, ſo neither is there any more than one God who is the immortal King of Ages.</p>
            <p>The Voice of our dead Prince therefore cries, Don't weep for me, but weep for your ſelves; conſider your own caſe, O Mortals! I ſhall come no more where you are, but you ſhall come where I am: And why are you afraid to come up hither? You are ſurrounded with a World that is involv'd and plung'd in Sin and Evil, and yet you are not willing to go out of it; and you have over your Heads a glorious Heaven, and yet are unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to aſcend thither. From this lofty Manſion, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am got, I behold your great Multitudes of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as ſo many buſy Ants, the World as a Shadow, and the Earth as a Point. I am here above your Enemies and Miſeries, above your Fears and Hopes, above your Covetouſneſs and Revenge, out of the reach of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies and Ingratitude, and all thoſe many Paſſions which divide all the Spaces of your Lives. I am here crowned with an incorruptible Diadem, ſeated upon a Throne that cannot be ſhaken, in the Boſom of God my Father, in the Company of Angels and Saints, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt my triumphant Forefathers. Prepare your ſelves therefore, and make ready to follow me; You who were ready and willing to follow me in the hotteſt and moſt dangerous Places of the Field, can you not reſolve to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me to this Abode of Glory, to this Place of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph?</p>
            <p>You who have this Opportunity to hear him crying and recommending things of this Importance, improve
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32536:9"/>and make good Uſe of this Voice of your dead Maſter; let him be this Day your Maſter in a new Senſe: and you that formerly were his Servants, become now his Diſciples; for certainly we ſhall never receive a more preſſing Advertiſement from Heaven, or that can fix in our Souls more ſharp Goads to ſpur us to a Contempt of this World.</p>
            <p>This ſame Voice addreſſeth it ſelf to all the Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Powers that God hath raiſed to a Throne; the Voice from Heaven cries, <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods, but ye ſhall die like Men.</hi> The Principalities and Powers of Heaven, which are the Angels, die not, becauſe they are not clothed with Fleſh; <hi>but it is appointed to all Men once to die,</hi> I ſay once only; for the Word of God ſhall reſcue us from Death, and ſhall make us to live again eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally with the Angels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Voice</hi> is, that of a <hi>young</hi> Prince, whom Death hath cropp'd when he was but beginning to bloſſom, and to ſhoot the firſt Buds of an extraordinary Vertue at the Age of Twenty four. Alas! why was this young Hero ſo ſoon ſnatch'd from us? becauſe, though young in Years, yet upon many Accounts he was ripe, not with reference to what he would have been had he liv'd longer, but to what others are at that Age, which is but the firſt quarter of Man's Life. O what Difference is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween twenty four and fourſcore, which is the term of Life the Prophet allots to the ſtrongeſt Men. O had it pleaſed God to have preſerv'd him till that term! how well would he have anſwered his Name? Poſterity read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his great Acts, would have demanded whether it were the Father, or the Son, or this our good Prince. But conſidering the Shortneſs of his Life, we may truly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32536:10"/>ſay, our rare, our wonderful Prince, had not his Peer in our Days.</p>
            <p>And being thus in his firſt Dawning, what Beams, what a Glory might not we juſtly have expected from his High-noon! His Spring having ſhew'd ſo fair and pompous, what Fruits, what Advantages ſhould not we have reap'd from his Autumn. But then he could not have cried, as he does now, <hi>All Fleſh is Graſs, and all the Glory thereof as the Flower of the Field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this who can warrant you that you ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live to morrow? You'll ſay, why my Youth, my hail Conſtitution, my Vigour and Strength. But, ſay I, was there ever any thing more gay, more lively, more bloom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than his Royal Highneſs was, full of good Blood, and a quick Fire: He was all Action, and all Life; he was like <hi>Jonathan,</hi> ſwift like an Eagle, ſtrong as a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but yet neither the one nor the other could deliver him. Go to now, vain Mortals, and ſacrifice to your Muſcles, and admire your Agility; as if Men of ſtrong and Athletick Conſtitutions had an Exemption from Death; and as if Glaſs that is new blown, was not as brittle as that which was made long before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The third Voice</hi> is that of a <hi>Great</hi> Prince; for Princes, like Stars, are ſome of them of the firſt Magnitude, ſome of the ſecond, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they are all of them Great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but not all Equal, for one excels the other in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. There be many Princes that are of a ſweet and good Temper, who yet are neither good nor great Princes, becauſe they want the Princely Vertues that are ſo neceſſary to the Good of their Subjects. But as for our Prince, Is there any of thoſe that knew him, dares ſay, that he was not of the higheſt Elevation, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32536:10"/>of the greateſt Magnitude? Alas! had he liv'd longer, what ſignal Proofs would he have given of it. From the Rock whence he was hewn, could proceed nothing but what was great on either ſide. God had favour'd him with lofty Heroical Motions, worthy of, and well becoming that Princely Spirit mention'd by the Prophet, Gifts very rare in our Age: But yet <hi>the Voice cries,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this Greatneſs and Excellency, <hi>he is dead,</hi> vaniſh'd and gone, and faded away like the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Field. Worſhip God therefore, both great and ſmall; and knowing that there is no Greatneſs can ſtand before him, without ſtooping to his Power, caſt down your Crowns at the Foot of his Throne, and do him Obeiſance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fourth Voice</hi> is that of <hi>our</hi> Prince, the moſt ſweet Voice, and yet the moſt bitter of all the reſt, and which properly is addreſs'd to us: The World laments him, but it is we have loſt him: Others bewail him, but alas we are deprived of him! and yet I know not by what Effect of a fatal Stupidity, we whom it concerns moſt, grieve leſs for him than they do. God grant I be not the Prophet of your Diſaſter; but whatever we may think, God never withdraws ſuch great Lights out of the World, but at the Approach of ſome black Tempeſt, which will certainly overtake us, <hi>if to day that we hear his Voice we harden our Hearts.</hi> If we prove inſenſible of this terrible Stroke God hath diſcharg'd on our Heads, he'll ſtrike the whole Body. He hath made a dreadful Step, but don't think he will ſtop there: for, <hi>behold he comes</hi> in theſe dark <hi>Clouds, and every Eye ſhall ſee him.</hi> If we will not be ſenſible of the Thunder he hath levell'd at our Heads, he'l lift up his Rod of Iron, and break
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32536:11"/>Arms and Limbs; and, together with the Head of Gold, will beat to pieces the Members of Silver, Braſs and Iron, <hi>and make them become like the Chaff of the Summer-threſhing Floors, which the Wind carries away,</hi> ſo that <hi>no Place ſhall be found for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Death hath taken away our Prince, but ſomething worſe than Death may take away our Provinces: His Magazien is not exhauſted, nor his Stores drawn dry, he hath other Darts to ſhoot beſides<note n="*" place="margin">The Prince di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Small-Pox.</note> the ſmall Pox; he will ſend his <hi>pale, black</hi> and <hi>red Horſe,</hi> Plague, War and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, that ſhall reap your Provinces, and avenge the Contempt of his Name: and if God hath ſpar'd you till now, if you be the laſt that ſhall drink of his Cup, which hath gone round the Nations, aſſure your ſelves, unleſs you prevent it by a timely Repentance, you ſhall drink the very Dregs and Bottom of it.</p>
            <p>Can you think that thoſe on whom the Tower of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loam</hi> fell in our Days, were worſe than you are, who make no other Return for his moſt ſignal Benefits, but that of Ingratitude, and who turn his Viſitations and Judgments into Plays and Paſquils! How greatly do you pleaſe the Devil and his Inſtruments by this your Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour? How do you double your Enemies Joys? and as if they had not ſufficient Cauſe of Triumph from our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſter, we afford them new Occaſions from our Ingratitude and Stupidity. We would willingly cry nothing but Bleſſing; but alas! what good Preſage can we draw from ſeeing many of us of the ſame Mind, and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame Wiſhes with our Adverſaries? Surely a moſt unhappy Sign it is to ſee us ſeconding the Deſires of our Enemies, and unſenſible of a Loſs which is likely to prove the occaſion of our utter Ruine.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:32536:11"/>
            <p>Who is able to conceive or expreſs the Deſolation to which that Houſe is reduc'd, which formerly ſhone with the Luſtre of ſo many glorious Lights? When theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions loſt their <hi>Maurice,</hi> they preſently lighted upon <hi>Frederick Henry,</hi> his moſt worthy Brother and Succeſſor; and when he was withdrawn too, you well remember how they immediately thereupon embraced Prince <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> his moſt worthy Son, who then wiped the Tears from your Eyes; and, like a beautiful riſing Sun, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd the Darkneſs and Shadows of your Night: but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof, at preſent, he draws Tears from your Eyes, and leaves behind him, as it were, a Sun ſet, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Hopes of a Return, the very Shadow of Death, which is the Night of Life.</p>
            <p>Not that he will want worthy Succeſſors, for the Blood of <hi>Naſſau</hi> is not extinct in his Veins; there are other Branches left ſtill, only there is never a Brother, never a Son as formerly, that yet appears in the World: We have no more in our Eyes, a Light like to thoſe two twin Stars called <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> whereof the one no ſooner ſets, but the other riſeth, and calms the Storm by a pleaſing Viciſſitude: We ſhall ſee no more a Phenix to be born of his Aſhes, an only Son appear upon the Throne, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the Death of a Father, who ſeem'd the only Glory of the World, and who yet would not have been ſo, had his Son liv'd longer: <q>But there is a Budco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd under the Earth, which, e're long, will ſhoot up like a Sprig from a dry Ground, which ſhall make his Name and our Hope to grow green and flouriſh again.</q> God grant it, God bring it to paſs, God be pleaſed to kindle again the Lamp of his Anointed, and cauſe our <hi>Lebanon</hi> to flouriſh.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:32536:12"/>
            <p>Though I cannot but own that theſe are things at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and very uncertain, very uncertain for the Event, and very remote as to their Enjoyment: for will it not be a Miracle of God, if the ſacred Fruit ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in ſo ſurious a Storm, in the midſt of ſuch rude Shakings, and ſuch terrible Convulſions; and after all, how many Years muſt paſs over our Heads before he be ripe, or capable of repreſenting to us his Father, his Grand-father, or Great Grand-father, or all three of them together? but yet ſo he does but come, we ſhall ſay, <hi>Tandem fit Surculus Arbor,</hi> the Sprig will at length come to be a Tree; and our Wiſhes and Bleſſings ſhall haſte forwards his Age and Vertue; ſo that we ſhall ſee him grow to the very Eye in Authority over Men, and Favour with God: for why may we not promiſe our ſelves from the Son, what we have ſeen in the Perſon of the Father? I call him Father, alas all trembling, in the Stile of a Prophet, who as yet hath never a Child; and I call him Son, who, it may be, will not be at all; or, it may be, not a Son; and who, for certain, will not ſee his Father, ſave at the Reſurrection. But we, we I ſay, have ſeen him antedating his Years, and anticipating our Expectations by Heroical, advanc'd and mature Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and in his firſt Seaſon, ſhewing in his Diſcourſes all the Prudence and Sagacity of conſummated old Age.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who have ſeen him in Buſineſs and in Council, have reaſon to know it better than we; and I take them to witneſs, whether they have not a thouſand times ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd the Gravity of his Youth, the Sweetneſs of his Fire, the Severity of his Joy, the Heat that animated him; and, on the other hand, the Prudence that reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. Even thoſe themſelves who never ſaw him but at ordinary Audiences, and in private Converſe, cannot
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32536:12"/>be ignorant neither of the Authority that his Eyes ſhed on his Diſcourſe, nor of the Grace that was poured forth on his Lips, nor of the Solidity of his Judgment, which he made appear every where to be well worthy of a four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Years Experience. In a word, ſuch he was, that if a Stranger ſhould have chanc'd at firſt to have ſeen him without his blew Ribbon, in a common Dreſs, amongſt a Crowd of Gentlemen, where he had only pronounced three Words, he muſt have been ſtupid, not to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſaid, That is the Prince.</p>
            <p>Even thoſe very Perſons who could not love, yet did admire him. When I ſpeak of thoſe who did not love him, I do not mean any Perſon in the midſt of us, for I cannot conceive any one amongſt us to be ſo great a Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to his Country, as not to love the Head and Prince which God had ſet over them. I ſpeak of Strangers: Do I ſay Strangers, when it is apparent that Strangers loved him as well as we; I mean his and our Enemies, who are equally ſworn Enemies of our Religion and his Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Family. They conſider'd him as a Head fatal to their Tyranny; the only, but univerſal Heir of that Name and Vertue, which has ſo often ſhook the Foundations of their Eſcurial. O how many ſecret Bonfires will they kindle in their Hearts! Can you queſtion their chanting an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Te Deum?</hi> They had nothing ſo precious where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they would not have been willing to purchaſe this piece of News. What would not they have given for the Advantage this Death hath caſt in upon them?</p>
            <p>Boaſt no more of your Trophies, nor ſo many Victories you have gained over them: Would to God <hi>Breda</hi> or <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricht</hi> were ſtill in their Hands, ſo we had but our Prince, who was of more Value to you than a whole Kingdom. We have now great reaſon to own that there is nothing ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32536:13"/>low, nothing ſo high, which is not levell'd by Death: You had the upper Hand both in War and Peace, and that in a glorious manner, over your Enemies: You were their Maſters, but this Death hath ſet you upon even Ground, and hath made them quit with you. When you ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to reckon up your Triumphs, your conquer'd Places, the Battels you have won, they will anſwer and daſh this with a <hi>You have no more your Prince of</hi> Orange. This only Word will be ſufficient to comfort all their Diſgraces, and to damp and mortify all your Joy and Glory.</p>
            <p>This Death alone may make you think that Peace ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous, which you had ſo much Difficulty to accept of. But what would have become of you, had your good Prince left you either before or during the Treaty of Peace? You would not have had ſo good Conditions from them, who have yielded you ſo much, yet had yielded nothing but for fear of his riſing Glory. In this caſe they would have been ſo far from owning you a Free People, that they would have ſtill treated you as Rebels; they would have rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded your Conqueſts, and you would have been fain calmly to yield them up; and whatſoever they have offer'd, the ſame they would have exacted of you: Yea, here I dare aſſert ſomething, which though it will not ſeem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable at firſt ſight, yet will be found very true in the Senſe I mean it. This Prince has been the Prince of your Peace; not that he wiſh'd for it, as a weak and puſillanimous Prince might have done, his martial Humour could never ſuffer him to be weary of the War, if he had not preferr'd the Publick Peace to his own Inclinations, which were all upon the wing for Glory, but becauſe the Apprehenſions which the Blood of <hi>Naſſau</hi> working and beating in his Veins, gave his Enemies, was the charming <hi>Caduceum</hi> that made them ſo compliant.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:32536:13"/>
            <p>The Father carryed on the War, and the Son made the Peace; the Father made you Victorious in the former, and the Son made you Arbitrator of the latter. The Father had carryed the Terror of his Arms into the heart of <hi>Spain;</hi> but he being no more, 'tis to his Son, in whom they ſaw him reviv'd, and from whom they feared all that they had ſo lately ſuffer'd, to which you owe, if not the Peace, at leaſt the Advantages of it: For who could have thought they would ever have ſtooped to ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantageous Conditions? And as he had procur'd it, ſo he likewiſe preſerv'd and maintain'd it; nor was there any fear your Enemies would ever break it, as long as this young Lyon was the Keeper of your fair Provinces; ſo deep an impreſſion had his Roaring already made upon their Spirits.</p>
            <p>How exceeding would have been your Joy, how great your Security, to have ſeen at the Head of your Armies, the Son and Grand-Son of your Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Defenders, like a young <hi>Caeſar,</hi> covering your Fields with the dead Bodies of your Tyrants, and his Hereditary Enemies, dying your Channels with their Blood, thundering, cruſhing, and breaking to pieces and ſhivers, whatſoever made the leaſt Pauſe in accepting his Yoak, or the leaſt Shew of oppoſing it ſelf to his Shock. You could not expect any thing leſs from that Great Heart, wherewith God had endow'd him, which was always in Action, and in a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and rapid Motion as that of the Sun and the Heavens.</p>
            <p>We do not ſay this to flatter him, or to pleaſe him; were he ſtill in the World, we ſhould not ſay it; but what is there left for us to praiſe, if it be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32536:14"/>not lawful for us to praiſe a Prince after his Death? In the Bleſſed State to which he is arrived amongſt the Saints and Angels, and his Triumphant Anceſtors, cover'd with a thouſand Lawrels, crown'd with a Diadem incorruptible; as he diſpenceth no Favours, ſo he wants none of our Praiſes: We ſpeak it only to ſatisfie Truth, and to awaken the drowſie ſenſes of ſome, who without any bad intention, but by a too great Concern for their Buſineſs and Petty In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, will ſhake their heads, and ſay, <hi>Well, God will raiſe us up another, all this will ſtill be for the best, and be a means of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting us more together:</hi> And God grant you may be more United, for ſure it is that He can make you ſo, without any Means, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that Prince, who was the Cement of your Union, the Captain of your Armies, the Terror of your Enemies, and the Tutelar Angel of your Dominions. But ſtill we muſt own, that this is ill ſpoken; for if we do not feel the ſtroaks God diſcharged on our heads, what is it we ſhall feel then? And if Crowns fell'd to the ground, do not make us afraid, we have reaſon to believe He will not ſtop there. But to proceed:</p>
            <p>We have juſt Cauſe to bemoan the Princeſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is a Mother, who has loſt her only Son, her Joy, and her Crown, the Fruit of her Education, and the Living Pourtraicture of her Vertues: But his other Mother, I mean the Church of God, muſt be the Principal Object of our Mourning; for She indeed hath loſt more than we do imagine, but ſhall know it one day; henceforward we ſhall ſee the Numbers of thoſe Idolaters encreaſed, which ſwarm in our days, and ſhall find a Sluce opened to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32536:14"/>Licentiouſneſs of Sects and Fanatical Opinions. We don't make a Saint or Demi-God of him, tho it be notorious that Old <hi>Rome</hi> hath Deified, and New <hi>Rome</hi> Canoniz'd ſuch as did not reach him for Worth. The Sun it ſelf hath its Spots, neither was he without the Faults of Great Princes; but he had acknowledg'd, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, and amended them; and ſhould we go about to compare him with the Princes of our Time, it would be an eaſie thing to prove, That our good Prince at the Age of Twenty Four, had not his Fellow in our days: And this being ſo, we muſt ſay our Rare, nay, our Admirable Prince.</p>
            <p>We will not enter upon Compariſons, but only ſay, That we moſtly extol Princes for their eaſineſs of Acceſs, Bounty, ſweetneſs of Temper and Affabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which indeed in themſelves are very commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Virtues, but not the Virtues of Princes; they are good, but for what? For any thing but Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: That Princely Spirit, thoſe Heroical Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and thoſe Great and Generous Thoughts, have not many Examples in our Age: Thus much we can Averr, That ours had ſo much of them, as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged him to love the Church of God, and to hate thoſe with a perfect Hatred, that troubled its Repoſe, or corrupted its Purity. We have this of certain knowledge, That he would never have been a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer of Errour or Faction: And is not this a Good of ineſtimable Value? <hi>Sion</hi> hath loſt the faireſt of her Ornaments, and the moſt precious of her Pillars; <hi>the Breath of our Noſtrils, he of whom we ſaid, we ſhall reſt under his ſhadow:</hi> The Whole Body of our Churches will feel this Blow, and put on Mourning for this our Prince. Our Churches in <hi>France,</hi> were
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32536:15"/>not ſo confin'd, but that they look'd upon our Prince with Joy, as being one of theirs, and doubt not but they are more ſenſible of this Stroak than we are.</p>
            <p>But all Words fail us when we come to caſt our eyes upon the deſolate young Princeſs, <hi>young,</hi> a <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> and <hi>with Child,</hi> and ſooner a Widow than a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; how many Swords have pierc'd her Soul? How many Calamities have beaten upon her, like ſo many crowding Waves one upon the back of another? What Deeps hath ſhe ſeen rowling over her, and ready to ſwallow her! Which way would you have her turn her ſelf? To the Continent? They are not concern'd at it: To the Iſles? She there ſees her Shipwrack round about her, ſhe there perceives nothing but a black Image of Death and Deſpair: She has nothing to direct her eyes to, but to Heaven; for ſhe can never ſo little caſt her eyes down to the Earth, but ſhe finds her ſelf obliged to groan for horror and ſorrow of heart; a Mother in Baniſhment, a Brother in Trouble, a Father upon the Scaffold, and to fill the Meaſure brimfull, a Husband in a Coffin. Let us draw a Curtain before, as <hi>Timantes</hi> of Old did, for this Sorrow admits no Colours. But do we think the Prince left <hi>One</hi> Onely Widow? He had indeed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed but one Wife, and yet hath left Eight Widows behind him. The Seven Provinces will accompany his Royal and Deſolate Spouſe, all in Tears, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with the ſame Mourning Aſhes.</p>
            <p>Let us all therefore ſmite upon our breaſts, and ſay with <hi>Jehoſhaphat; O Lord our God, we know not what to do, but our eyes are towards thee: 'Tis thou who looſeſt the Bells of Kings, and who bringeſt down from the Throne into the Duſt. 'Tis thou who haſt their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32536:15"/>hearts in thy hand, and putſt thy breath into their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils. 'Tis thou who ſaidſt to Princes, I have ſaid ye are Gods, but ye ſhall dye like men. We acknowledge before thee, that our ſins have drawn down thy Judgments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and that thou haſt juſtly ſuffered the Crown to fall from our heads, becauſe we have trod thy Commandments under our feet. 'Tis true, O Lord, that we have too much truſted in that Arm, which we now experience was but an Arm of fleſh, inſtead of having our eye to that great Arm of Heaven, which hath ſupported us, and can ſtill ſupport us, as well as it upholds the Earth without any other prop or ſtay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>True it is, we have too much ſacrificed to our nets, and ſitting down under the ſhadow of our own Power, have not ſought as we ought, our ſafety under the covert of thy wings. Wherefore alſo thou hast ſnatch'd him away from us, woe unto us that we have ſinned! But in the midſt of thy wrath, O Lord remember mercy. Look down with pity, and ſpare a Houſe, which of ſo long a time hath been the Ornament and Stay of thine, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt part of thine Inheritance, the refuge of thy Ark, and the Tabernacle of thy Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Raiſe to thy Servant a just ſeed, that may rebuild thy Temple. Thou who art the Prince of Life, who holdeſt in thy hands the iſſues of Life and Death, open to him the Gates of Life; preſerve this Royal Slip, as of old thou didſt</hi> Moſes <hi>in an Ark of Bulruſhes beaten with the winds, and at the mercy of the Waves; comfort the Widow big with Child, ſtrengthen her heart in this hard Tryal to which thou haſt been pleaſed to reduce her; open the eyes, and bleſs the endeavours of our Magiſtrates, and grant that in this great Eclipſe, we may by the compaſs of their prudent and ſteady Conduct, meet with the Remedy of our Evils.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:32536:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vouchſafe to us all, the Grace to deſpiſe the hollow empty Figure of this World, and all its illuſions, <hi>the Fleſh with all its Glory,</hi> that from henceforth we may place our Hopes in thee alone, who art the great Prince of our Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Holy and Wiſe Ruler of the World, govern us by the Sceptre of thy Word, and of thy Holy Truth, till Princes and Provinces, Magiſtrates and People, Paſtors and Flocks, being gathered together in thy Heavenly</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>there to enjoy the glorious Liberty of thy Son, may Eternally Aſcribe to thee, Honour, Power and Bleſſing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:32536:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
